<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic
  id="declarationterminology"
  xml:lang="en-us">
  <title>Declaration terminology</title>
  <shortdesc>When the model is expressed in a DTD or schema, various element types are declared. </shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>When referring to the element-type declarations, the following terminology is
      used:<draft-comment>JTH: Define specialized element, specialized attribute
        here?</draft-comment></p>
    <dl>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>Element declaration</dt>
        <dd> The representation within a schema technology (such as DTD, XML Schema, or Relax NG)
          for an element type.</dd>
      </dlentry>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>Attribute declaration</dt>
        <dd> The representation within a schema technology (such as DTD, XML Schema, or Relax NG)
          for an attribute type.</dd>
      </dlentry>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>Type module</dt>
        <dd>The representation within a schema technology for the element and attribute types
          uniquely defined by a topic type, map type, or domain.</dd>
      </dlentry>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>Topic module</dt>
        <dd>The representation within a schema technology for the element types uniquely defined
          by a topic type.</dd>
      </dlentry>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>Map module</dt>
        <dd>The representation within a schema technology for the element types uniquely defined
          by a map type.</dd>
      </dlentry>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>Structural module</dt>
        <dd>A topic or map module.</dd>
      </dlentry>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>Domain module</dt>
        <dd>The representation within a schema technology for the element types or attribute type
          uniquely defined by a domain.</dd>
      </dlentry>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>Document type shell, head schema</dt>
        <dd>The representation within a schema technology for a DTD shell or head schema that
          declares no element or attribute types itself (except potentially for a &lt;dita> root
          element that allows multiple peer topic types in the same document type) but points to
          and assembles topic and domain modules or map and domain modules.<draft-comment
            author="MP"
            disposition="completed"
            time="06/09/19">Added mention of dita common pattern per Jeff
            Ogden</draft-comment><draft-comment>MP added "head schema" terminology after review of
              schema module organization topic</draft-comment></dd>
      </dlentry>
      <dlentry>
        <dt>Document type declaration</dt>
        <dd> The representation within a schema technology for a document type. The document type
          declaration includes the declaration modules assembled by the document declaration
          shell.</dd>
      </dlentry>
    </dl>
    <fig>
      <title>Diagram of Declaration Terminology</title>
    </fig>
  </body>
</topic>
