<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">
<concept
  id="newDomain">
  <title>Domain specialization pattern</title>
  <conbody>
    <section
      id="section_04EBD53C7C3B43B0AC495952905D4EF1">
      <p>The name of the domain type schema document consists of the domain name plus <filepath
          >Domain</filepath>plus the <filepath>.xsd</filepath> extension, e.g., <filepath
          >highlightDomain.xsd</filepath>.</p>
      <p>As in a structural module, the domain module must define each specialized element, its
        attributes, and its model groups. As with any specialization, the domain element must
        restrict the base element. The class attribute of the domain element must start with a plus
        sign but, otherwise, follows the same rules as the class attribute for an element introduced
        by a topic specialization. </p>
      <p>For each element extended by one or more domains, the domain type schema document defines a
        model group for the base element. The definition of the model group is a disjunctive list of
        alternatives beginning with the literal name of the element and including the element
        extension entity name from each domain that is providing specializations. </p>
      <p>The schema document must define an a model group for each element extended by the domain.
        The contents of the model group must be the list of specialized elements for the extended
        element. The name of the model group is the abbreviation for the domain plus the name of the
        extended element separated by a hyphen. In the following example, the user interface domain
        (abbreviated as <codeph>ui-d</codeph>) extends the <codeph>ph</codeph>
        element.<codeblock>&lt;xs:group name="ui-d-ph"&gt;
          &lt;xs:choice&gt;
          &lt;xs:element ref="uicontrol" /&gt;
          &lt;xs:element ref="menucascade" /&gt;
          &lt;/xs:choice&gt; 
          &lt;/xs:group&gt;</codeblock></p>
    </section>
  </conbody>
</concept>
